Speaker 1: Hey everybody, Peter Zahn here coming to you from the Chicago Lakeshore.
Speaker 1: Today's topic is China's difficulty in securing energy supplies from really about anywhere.
Speaker 1: The trigger for me for this one is something that happened a couple weeks ago.
Speaker 1: We had one of the regional chiefs of a group called TTP, the name is right here,
Speaker 1: also known as the Pakistani Taliban.
Speaker 1: Now, for those of you who have not blocked out the entire 20 years of the war on terror,
Speaker 1: you'll remember the TTP was one of the groups that really plagued the United States
Speaker 1: in getting supplies from the Guar port in western Pakistan up into Afghanistan.
Speaker 1: A secondary route was going for Karachi North.
Speaker 1: TTP controls a lot of the countryside.
Speaker 1: A lot of western and especially northern Pakistan is dry to desert and rugged and mountainous.
Speaker 1: And so you can easily have a militant group that just snarls supply lines.
Speaker 1: Anyway, this guy, a couple weeks ago, said that he's perfectly willing to allow the Chinese
Speaker 1: to build their massive infrastructure project through Pakistan as long as his tribe gets 5% protection money.
Speaker 1: Which, you know, is kind of novel that he's got a business model like that.
Speaker 1: Anyway, he means it and he's made it very clear that he and his people are willing to attack
Speaker 1: the infrastructure, the construction sites, and the workers.
Speaker 1: He made that very explicit in his statements.
Speaker 1: And it kind of leaves the Chinese reeling.
Speaker 1: One of the things that people forget about the Chinese is there's always this weird assumption
Speaker 1: in the West and China is that China is somehow different from all of the powers that have come before.
Speaker 1: And if you just introduce a new major power to the area,
Speaker 1: everyone's going to just buddy up to them because they're not what came before.
Speaker 1: And that's just never true.
Speaker 1: The Chinese generate just as much mal-feeling as everybody else.
Speaker 1: And they're seen as just another imperial power in most zones.
Speaker 1: And for the Chinese, this has always been more of a problem than has been for the Western powers.
Speaker 1: Because if you're Britain or France or Spain or any of the old imperial set,
Speaker 1: yes, there's always issues with getting access to energy.
Speaker 1: But you're relatively proximate to a lot of them.
Speaker 1: So, for example, if you're, say, just France, you know, Algeria is right across the Mediterranean as is Libya.
Speaker 1: Ah, go around the bulge of Africa and you're in Nigeria.
Speaker 1: Or you can go over to Suez and all of a sudden you're in the Middle East and the Persian Gulf region.
Speaker 1: And so there's a crude of plenty.
Speaker 1: There's multiple routes to choose from.
Speaker 1: And not that any of them are super easy, but it's not like any of them are super complicated.
Speaker 1: Even for the United States, back in the days before shale, when we had to import a lot,
Speaker 1: we could go from the West Coast to Southeast Asia.
Speaker 1: We'd go south to Mexico and Latin America.
Speaker 1: Or you'd go east to all those normal places in Africa and the Middle East.
Speaker 1: There were options. There were always options.
Speaker 1: And that meant that the United States, even if you ignore the fact that it rules the oceans,
Speaker 1: still had options for keeping the lights on.
Speaker 1: Chinese have never had that.
Speaker 1: By the time that China expanded to the point that it needed all the energy,
Speaker 1: Southeast Asia was already largely tapped.
Speaker 1: So they need to go around Singapore, by India, and into the Persian Gulf,
Speaker 1: where they have to deal with either the Iranians or the Saudis or the Kuwaitis or whoever else.
Speaker 1: And that's really been the only play.
Speaker 1: It has always been the only play.
Speaker 1: And that means they've had a hard time with security.
Speaker 1: So we're posting with this video a graphic that was originally in my second book, Absent Superpower,
Speaker 1: that we've updated with more current data.
Speaker 1: This is the best data we have as of the point that COVID hit.
Speaker 1: Because after that, the data is bleh.
Speaker 1: It'll be a couple more years before we get post-COVID data that's any good.
Speaker 2: And it gives you an idea of just the scale, the volume, and the range that the Chinese have to deal with in order to get fuel.
Speaker 2: So starting west to east, you've got the Persian Gulf where they find themselves having to pick sides.
Speaker 1: Everyone thinks that they're going to go with the Iranians because the Saudis have traditionally been more pro-American.
Speaker 1: But Saudis export an order of magnitude almost more crude than the Iranians.
Speaker 1: Not to mention that if you side with the Iranians that you're going to have problems with the Kuwaitis or the Qataris or the Omanis.
Speaker 1: There's no clear answer here, except for to try to replace the United States as the dominant power within the Persian Gulf.
Speaker 2: And the Chinese absolutely lack the military reach to do that.
Speaker 2: Then, assuming they can get past all of those local problems, they have to get by India,
Speaker 2: which I don't know if you've been following the news, but for the last 80 years,
Speaker 2: the Indians and the Chinese haven't much cared for one another.
Speaker 2: And while the Indian Navy is not great, the Indian Navy operates by India.
Speaker 2: And so there's nothing, nothing that the Chinese could do if it came into a fight to protect their civilian shipping there.
Speaker 2: Then they have to get by Singapore, which is a tight American ally,
Speaker 2: and each even maintains a berth for American supercarriers.
Speaker 2: They go within range of the missile systems that the Australians have.
Speaker 2: They go by the coast of Vietnam, who hates, hates, hates, hates them so much.
Speaker 2: They go by the Philippines, which is another U.S. ally.
Speaker 2: And if you want to get into northern China, you now have to go by Taiwan.
Speaker 2: And again, if you haven't been following the news, Taiwan and China don't get along very well.
Speaker 2: And this whole time, you have to deal with both the American Navy and the Japanese Navy,
Speaker 2: which may have fewer ships, but they have longer range and more lethality.
Speaker 2: So there's, there's no solution here on the water.
Speaker 2: The hope with Pakistan is that eventually you can build an infrastructure corridor from Pakistan up over the mountains and into western China,
Speaker 2: where you can at least bypass those latter series of obstacles.
Speaker 2: The problem here is that running a pipe up and over mountain passes is really, really hard.
Speaker 2: That's why no one does it right now.
Speaker 2: And now if you've got local terrorists, they're just deciding to blow everything up.
Speaker 2: It's just one more problem.
Speaker 1: So if there was an easy solution here, it would have been found decades ago, but there's not.
Speaker 1: Which means that China remains the most vulnerable power of all of the major powers throughout human history.
Speaker 1: They're completely dependent upon an international security arrangement that they can't protect,
Speaker 3: they can't influence, and certainly can't replace.
Speaker 4: Oh, one more thing.
Speaker 4: Well, a lot of this news is bad.
Speaker 4: I mean, very bad for the Chinese.
Speaker 1: In fact, worse than it is for any of the other major powers.
Speaker 1: It's not all negative.
Speaker 1: China's problem was with liquid fuels that are derived from oil.
Speaker 1: So jet fuel, gasoline, diesel, things like that.
Speaker 1: Those are the things that they're going to lose access to at scale.
Speaker 1: But solid fuels, most notably coal, soft, brown, low-quality coal,
Speaker 1: is something they have in huge volumes at home.
Speaker 1: So even in the worst-case scenario for external security situations and energy crises,
Speaker 1: they're still going to be able to produce coal for their own domestic system.
Speaker 1: So if you're willing to put up with just ridiculous carbon emissions
Speaker 1: and atrocious air quality,
Speaker 1: the Chinese do have the ability to keep the lights on.
Speaker 1: They can generate electricity for all of their needs.
Speaker 1: That's not going to save them from all of the other problems.
Speaker 1: But at least they won't be suffering in the cold and in the dark.